Center on English Learning and Achievement (CELA); Records ua680.030
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
National Research Center on English Learning and Achievement (CELA) Records
1988-1999
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
National Research Center on English Learning & Achievement (U.S.)
ua680.030
1.0 cubic ft.
The Center on English Learning & Achievement (CELA) specializes in research, development, and services to improve literacy teaching and learning across the grades and subjects.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
Web Archives
Access
Access to this record group is unrestricted.
Acquisition Information
All items in this manuscript group were donated to the University Libraries, M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives, by CELA.
Biographical History
Founded in 1988 as the National Research Center on Literature Teaching and Learning, the Center's scope and focus was broadened in March 1996, as a result of a grant from the U.S. Department of Education. Renamed to the National Research Center on English Learning and Achievement, CELA is dedicated to improving the teaching and learning of English and language arts. CELA's research seeks to learn what elements of curriculum, instruction, and assessment are essential to developing high literacy and how schools can best help students achieve success. The organization provides that information to teachers, schools, and communities so that they can choose the approaches that will work with their students.
Scope and Contents
Includes the Center's published reports 1988-1995.
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection has no series, arranged alphabetically.
Literature; English--Education; Web Archives; UAlbany Centers & Institutes; National Research Center on English Learning & Achievement (U.S.); State University of New York at Albany; Applebee, Arthur
- Web Archives, 1997 June 7-2016 September 17; 1; 799 captures
  Immediate Source of Acquisition
  Web crawling is managed through the Internet Archive's Archive-It service. This page includes links to both the university's collection and the Internet Archive's public collection.
  Surface-level crawling of www.albany.edu is performed daily which should includes most top-level webpages. Separate targeted crawls of every albany.edu subdomain are performed monthly to attempt to gather all content. This includes: www.albany.edu, www.rna.albany.edu, www.ctg.albany.edu, www.ualbanysports.com, www.albany.edu/rockefeller, www.albany.edu/cela, www.albany.edu/asrc, m.albany.edu, library.albany.edu, events.albany.edu, cstar.cestm.albany.edu, csda.albany.edu, and alumni.albany.edu
  Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
  Web Archives
  - http://www.albany.edu/cela/ - University Archives collection, 2013 May 8-2016 September 17 (Web-archive 1)
  - WARC file for http://www.albany.edu/cela/, (please see https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Web_ARChive for more details), 2013 May 8-2016 September 17 (Warc 1)
    Conditions Governing Access
    WARC files are very large and difficult to work with. Your request may take time to process, and we may be unable to deliver your request remotely. Please consult an archivist if you are interested in researching with web archives.
  - http://www.albany.edu/cela/ - Internet Archive collection, 1997 June 7-2016 September 17 (Web-archive 2)
- Administrative Records, 1988-1999; 2; 1.0 cubic ft.
  - Applebee, A. A Study of Book-Length Works Taught in High School English Courses, 1989 (Box 1 (2-Administrative Records), Folder 1)
  - Applebee, A. The Teaching of Literature in Programs with Reputations for Excellence in English, 1989 (Box 1 (2-Administrative Records), Folder 2)
  - Applebee, A. Literature Instruction in American Schools, 1990 (Box 1 (2-Administrative Records), Folder 3)
  - Applebee, A. A Study of High School Literature Anthologies, 1991 (Box 1 (2-Administrative Records), Folder 4)
  - Applebee, A. Beyond the Lesson: Reconstructing Curriculum as a Domain for Culturally Significant Conversations, 1993 (Box 1 (2-Administrative Records), Folder 5)
  - Adams, H. The Difficulty of Difficulty, 1990 (Box 1 (2-Administrative Records), Folder 6)
  - Afferbach, P. and P. Johnston. Writing Language Arts Report Cards: Eleven Teachers' Conflicts of Knowing and Communicating, 1992 (Box 1 (2-Administrative Records), Folder 7)
  - Beach, R. and S. Hynds. Research on the Learning and Teaching of Literature: Selected Bibliography, 1989 (Box 1 (2-Administrative Records), Folder 8)
  - Blau, S. Building Bridges Between Literary Theory and the Teaching of Literature, 1993 (Box 1 (2-Administrative Records), Folder 9)
  - Bradley, J. Selected Bibliography of Materials and Approaches in the Learning and Teaching of Literature, Undated (Box 1 (2-Administrative Records), Folder 10)
  - Knoblauch, circa and L. Brannon. Teaching Literature in High School: A Teacher-Research Project, 1990 (Box 1 (2-Administrative Records), Folder 11)
  - DeFabio, R. Classroom as Text: Reading, Interpreting, and Critiquing, 1990 (Box 1 (2-Administrative Records), Folder 12)
  - Burke, S. Will Blake: Teaching and Learning Huckleberry Finn, 1990 (Box 1 (2-Administrative Records), Folder 13)
  - Chafe, W. Sources of Difficulty in the Processing of Written Language, 1990 (Box 1 (2-Administrative Records), Folder 14)
  - Close, E. How Did We Get Here: Seventh-Graders Sharing Literature, 1990 (Box 1 (2-Administrative Records), Folder 15)
  - Connolly, A. Taking the Fear Away from Learning: Observations of Contemporary Fiction Taught by Carol Johnson at the Chestnut Hill School in a City in New York, 1989 (Box 1 (2-Administrative Records), Folder 16)
  - Danaher, J. Pullin' It All Together Karen Dunne: One Woman Workin' Too Hard, 1991 (Box 1 (2-Administrative Records), Folder 17)
  - DeFabio, R. Classroom as Text: Reading, Interpreting, and Critiquing a Literature Class, 1989 (Box 1 (2-Administrative Records), Folder 18)
  - DeLawter, J. Teaching Literature: From Clerk to Explorer, 1990 (Box 1 (2-Administrative Records), Folder 19)
  - Dias, P. Literary Reading and Classroom Constraints: Aligning Practice with Theory, 1990 (Box 1 (2-Administrative Records), Folder 20)
  - Elam, H. The Difficulty of Reading, 1990 (Box 1 (2-Administrative Records), Folder 21)
  - Forman-Pemberton circa Being There With Kevin Tucker, 1989 (Box 1 (2-Administrative Records), Folder 22)
  - McGill-Franzen, A. and circa Lanford. Exposing the Edge of the Preschool Curriculum: Teachers' Talk about Text and Children's Literary Understandings, 1993 (Box 1 (2-Administrative Records), Folder 23)
  - Hansson, G. Reading and Literature, 1990 (Box 1 (2-Administrative Records), Folder 24)
  - Hansbury-Zuendt, T. Voices Making Meaning: Reading the Texts with Tony Carrera, 1989 (Box 1 (2-Administrative Records), Folder 25)
  - Hynds, S. Questions of Difficulty in Literary Reading, 1991 (Box 1 (2-Administrative Records), Folder 26)
  - Hynds, S. Challenging Questions in the Literature Classroom, 1990 (Box 1 (2-Administrative Records), Folder 27)
  - Johnston, P., P. Weiss and P. Afferbach. Teachers' Evaluations of Teaching and Learning of Literacy and Literature, 1990 (Box 1 (2-Administrative Records), Folder 28)
  - Langer, J. Discussion as Exploration: Literature and the Horizon of Possibilities, 1991 (Box 1 (2-Administrative Records), Folder 29)
  - Langer, J. The Process of Understanding Literature, 1989 (Box 1 (2-Administrative Records), Folder 30)
  - Langer, J. Literary Understanding and Literature Instruction, 1991 (Box 1 (2-Administrative Records), Folder 31)
  - Langer, J. The Process of Understanding Literature. REPRINTED, 1989 (Box 1 (2-Administrative Records), Folder 32)
  - Marshall, J. Patterns of Discourse in Classroom Discussions of Literature, 1989 (Box 1 (2-Administrative Records), Folder 33)
  - Marshall, J., M. Klaques and R. Fehlman. Discussions of Literature in Middle-Track Classrooms, 1991 (Box 1 (2-Administrative Records), Folder 34)
  - Marhafer, D. The Heart and Soul of the Class, 1989 (Box 1 (2-Administrative Records), Folder 35)
  - Miller, S. Creating Change: Towards a Dialogic Pedagogy, 1992 (Box 1 (2-Administrative Records), Folder 36)
  - Nystrand, M. Making It Hard: Curriculum and Instruction as Factors in Difficulty of Literature, 1990 (Box 1 (2-Administrative Records), Folder 37)
  - Petrosky, A. To Teach (Literature), 1991 (Box 1 (2-Administrative Records), Folder 38)
  - Probst, R. Five Kinds of Literary Knowing, 1990 (Box 1 (2-Administrative Records), Folder 39)
  - Purcell-Gates, V. On the Outside Looking In: A Study of Remedial Readers' Meaning-Making While Reading Literature, 1990 (Box 1 (2-Administrative Records), Folder 40)
  - Purves, A. Indeterminate Texts, Responsive Readers, and the Idea of Difficulty in Literature Learning, 1990 (Box 1 (2-Administrative Records), Folder 41)
  - Brody, P., circa Demilo and A. Purves. The Current State of Assessment in Literature, 1989 (Box 1 (2-Administrative Records), Folder 42)
  - Purves, A., H. Li, V. McCann and P. Renken. Student Perceptions of Achievement in School Literature, 1991 (Box 1 (2-Administrative Records), Folder 43)
  - Purves, A., H. Li and M. Shirk. Comparison of Measures of the Domain of Learning in Literature, 1990 (Box 1 (2-Administrative Records), Folder 44)
  - Purves, A., H. Li and M. Shirk. Prototype Measures of the Domain of Learning in Literature, 1991 (Box 1 (2-Administrative Records), Folder 45)
  - Quick, D. The Teacher as mentor-Guide: Joe Allen on Antigone., Undated (Box 1 (2-Administrative Records), Folder 46)
  - Quick, D. The Mythmaker of Seneca, 1990 (Box 1 (2-Administrative Records), Folder 47)
  - Roberts, D., J. Langer and D. Strickland. Supporting the Process of Literary Understanding: Analysis of a Classroom Discussion, 1991 (Box 1 (2-Administrative Records), Folder 48)
  - Touponce, W. Literary Theory and the Notion of Difficulty, 1990 (Box 1 (2-Administrative Records), Folder 49)
  - Walmsley, S., A. Bronk and K. Weiss. School Book Clubs as Literacy Development: A Descriptive Study, 1994 (Box 1 (2-Administrative Records), Folder 50)
  - Walmsley, S.and T. Walp. Teaching Literature in Elementary School, 1989 (Box 1 (2-Administrative Records), Folder 51)
  - Walmsley, S. and L. Fielding. A Study of Second Graders' Home and School Literary Experience, 1991 (Box 1 (2-Administrative Records), Folder 52)
  - # 1.8. Purves, A. Towards a Revaluation of Reader Response and School Literature, 1993 (Box 1 (2-Administrative Records), Folder 53)
  - # 1.9. Allington, R. Reducing the Risk Integrating Language Arts in Restructured Elementary Schools, 1993 (Box 1 (2-Administrative Records), Folder 54)
  - # 1.10. Applebee, A. Toward Thoughtful Curriculum: Fostering Discipline-Based Conversation in the English Language Arts Classroom, 1994 (Box 1 (2-Administrative Records), Folder 55)
  - # 1.11. Applebee, A., R. Burroughs and A. Stevens. Shaping Conversations: A Study of Continuity and Coherence in High School Literature Curricula, 1994 (Box 1 (2-Administrative Records), Folder 56)
  - # 1.12. Allington, R. The Schools We Have, The Schools We Need, 1994 (Box 1 (2-Administrative Records), Folder 57)
  - # 2.19. Langer, J., circa Confer and M. Sawyer. Teaching Disciplinary Thinking in Academic Coursework, 1993 (Box 1 (2-Administrative Records), Folder 58)
  - # 2.21. McGill-Franzen, A. and circa Lanford. Exposing the Edge of the Preschool Curriculum: Teachers' Talk about Text and Children's Literary Understandings, 1993 (Box 1 (2-Administrative Records), Folder 59)
  - # 2.30. Guice, S. and G. Brooks. Access Denied: A Five-Year Study of Literacy Instruction Provided to Poor, Urban Elementary Children, 1997 (Box 1 (2-Administrative Records), Folder 60)
  - # 2.32. Swan, K. and circa Meskill. Multimedia and Response-Based Literature Teaching and Learning, 1997 (Box 1 (2-Administrative Records), Folder 61)
  - # 3.7. Kolanowski, K. Use of Portfolios in Assessment of Literature, 1997 (Box 1 (2-Administrative Records), Folder 62)
  - # 3.8. DeFabio, R. Characteristics of Student Performance as Factors in Portfolio Assessment, 1993 (Box 1 (2-Administrative Records), Folder 63)
  - # 3.9. Jordan, S.and A. Purves. The Metaphor of the Portfolio and the Metaphors in Portfolios: The Relation of Classroom-Based to Large-Scale Assessment, 1994 (Box 1 (2-Administrative Records), Folder 64)
  - # 3.10. Galbraith, M., J. Hennelly and A. Purves. Using Portfolios to Negotiate a Rhetorical Community, 1994 (Box 1 (2-Administrative Records), Folder 65)
  - # 7.3. Jordan, S. and A. Purves. Issues in the Responses of Students to Culturally Diverse Texts: A Preliminary Study, 1993 (Box 1 (2-Administrative Records), Folder 66)
  - # 7.9. Cliff, circa and S. Miller. Multicultural Dialogue in Literature-History Classes: The Dance of Creative and Critical Thinking, 1997 (Box 1 (2-Administrative Records), Folder 67)
  - # 7.10. Tryzna, G. and S. Miller. A Case Study of Learning in an Integrated Literature-History Class: Personal Narrative, Critical Reflection, and Kris's Way of Knowing, 1997 (Box 1 (2-Administrative Records), Folder 68)
  - # 7.11. Langer, J. Literacy Acquisition Through Literature, 1997 (Box 1 (2-Administrative Records), Folder 69)